Guide to the Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park Records 1916-1938 (Bulk 1916-1931) MS 139
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park Records
1916-1938 (Bulk 1916-1931)
MS 139
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
5.5 Linear feet (11 boxes)
The Records of the Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park contain a variety of documents concerning the formation of the League and their activities regarding the preservation of Riverside Park and Upper West Side Improvement Plan. The collection contains correspondence, pamphlets, annual reports, clipping scrapbooks, minutes, cashbooks, and photographic materials.
Provenance
Donation, Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park, 1938.
Access Restrictions
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park also produced a number of additional records including clippings scrapbooks, minutes, and reports. These materials are separated from the material included in this guide and included in the general collections. The related materials are searchable in the New-York Historical Society's
online catalog.
For additional information, please contact New-York Historical Society library staff.
Historical Note
Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park was formed in May of 1916 with the objective to protect Riverside Park from proposed landscape alterations brought forth by the New York Central Railroad Company and the City of New York. Upon its establishment in 1916, an Executive Board consisting of mostly residents from the Upper West Side was established. Mrs. Charles Austin Bryan was the founding President. The five founding Vice Presidents were Mrs. James M. Stewart, Mrs. John Clapperton Kerr, Mrs. Arthur Melville Shrady, Mrs. John Caldwell Coleman, and Mrs. William R. Stewart. Members and individuals supporting the League's mission and activities primarily resided in the Upper West Side neighborhood. By 1918, the League represented over five hundred members. The first luncheon of the League was held on May 18, 1921 at the Claremont.
In 1916, the League primarily advocated for provisions to protect the park from the developments of the Port and Terminal facilities of New York City. These developments were the result of New York Central Railroad Company's West Side Improvement Plan, one of the largest projects undertaken jointly by public and private interests in Manhattan. The plan proposed developments to cover the railroad north of 72nd Street, construct an express motor highway, and create an additional 32 acres of recreational space for the public. The City of New York and the New York Central Railroad Company reached an agreement on July 2, 1929 concerning the Improvement Project. The Improvement Plan was dedicated on July 18, 1934 and completed in 1937.
The League was engaged with many matters concerning the planning and negotiations of the West Side Improvement Project, especially with matters concerning Riverside Park. Large portions of records in the collection reflect exchanges between the League and representatives of the West Side Improvement Engineering Committee. The Engineering Committee included representatives from the Board of Transportation, the Transit Commission, the Board of Estimate and Apportionment, the Borough of Manhattan, the Port of New York Authority, and the New York Central Railroad Company. The League was successful in negotiations with the Park Department and New York Central Railroad Company for the construction of foundations and walls covering the tracks as far as 82nd Street, the restoration of the southerly end of Riverside Park, provisions for boating and recreational facilities along the river, the removal of shacks along the river front and coal pockets from 96th Street, and the paving of the promenade north of 96th Street.
The League was also involved in park projects that promoted civic improvement and environmental preservation. In 1926, the League dedicated the area of Riverside Park extending from 116th to 124th Streets as an area called the "Memorial Grove of States." The League planted 72 trees, a memorial tree to an unknown solider of each state in the Union, the District of Columbia, Alaska, and Puerto Rico, in addition to planting 19 trees as a memorial to special patriots. The League also had an area in the park they referred to as the Bird Sanctuary. The League recorded the variety of migratory birds in the Sanctuary during its early years.
The League was involved in a variety of projects promoting the Park's significant role in the lives of children and residents of New York City. From the early days of the League, the League had an interest in the children in public and private schools, and the care and protection of the parks. Troop 599 Boy Scouts of America patrolled the Groves daily. The school children of public schools Nos. 54 and 179 planted trees in the park. The league encouraged children to make bird houses for placement in the trees in Riverside Park. They held birdhouse and poster contests. There was an exhibition of birdhouses and posters at the American Museum of Natural History, at the Columbia Yacht Club, and the Exposition of Women's Arts.
On November 18, 1938, the final meeting of the League's Executive board was held. The League's surplus funds were given to the Audubon Society for the care of the Bird Sanctuary and to the Park Department for the care of the Memorial Graves. The content in the League's records demonstrate the following two variants of the League's name: the Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park and the Women's League for the Protection of Riverside Park.
Scope and Content Note
The majority of records include correspondence and related ephemera concerning the activities of the League's executive board members, primarily Mrs. Charles Austin Bryan and Mrs. Helen Culver Kerr (Mrs. John Clapperton Kerr). The bulk of the collection includes correspondence and related documents that primarily address the encroachment of the New York Central tracks on Riverside Park, and the City of New York's Board of Estimate and Apportionment involvements in plans regarding the Upper West Side Improvement. The materials also include photographs of Riverside Park, and the League's activities in the Park. The collection includes two cashbooks, one minute book, and a variety of clippings scrapbooks of the League's activities and civic interests. Oversized materials include a variety of maps and blueprints concerning Riverside Park and the West Side Improvement Plan.
Arrangement Note
The records primarily reflect the original filing system of the League.
The records are divided into 5 series:
Series I: Correspondence of the Executive Board, (1916-1936)
Series II: Photographs (1926-1930, undated)
Series III: Administrative Books (1916-1931)
Series IV: Maps and Blueprints (1924-1932)
Series V: Newspaper Clipping Scrapbooks (1920-1936)
American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society.; Bryan, Mrs. Charles Austin; Ethical Culture School of New York City; Fredrick Law Olmstead (Firm).; Kerr, Helen Culver; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.). Office of the President.; Marks, Marcus M.; Municipal Art Society of New York.; New York (N.Y.) Dept. of Parks.; New York (N.Y.). Board of Estimate.; New York Central Railroad Company.; New York City Federation of Women's Clubs.; New York State College of Forestry at Syracuse University.; Vitale, Ferruccio, 1875-1933.; Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park.; Women's League for the Protection of Riverside Park.; Annual reports; Annuals (publications); Black-and-white photographs; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Cashbooks; Civic improvement -- New York (State) -- New York.; Cliches-verre (negatives); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Drafts (documents); Ephemera; Invitations; Landscape protection - New York (State) - New York.; Legal documents; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) --1900-1930.; Minute Books; Minutes; New York Central Railroad Company.; Pamphlets; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York - History - 20th century.; Railroads -- New York (State) -- New York.; Riverside Drive (New York, N.Y.); Riverside Park (New York, N.Y.); Scrapbooks; Trees -- New York (State) -- New York.; Upper West Side (New York, N.Y.); Waterfronts -- New York (State) -- New York.; West Side Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Women -- Societies and Clubs - New York (State) -- New York.
- Series I: Correspondence of the Executive Board, 1916-1936
  Scope and Contents note
  Summary:
  The majority of materials in this series include reports and correspondence from private and government bodies concerning the West Side Improvement Plan and the proposed changes to Riverside Park. The materials include correspondence between Mrs. John Clapperton Kerr, and Marcus M. Marks, the President of the City of New York's Borough of Manhattan. Also included is correspondence between Mrs. John Clapperton Kerr and the City of New York's Department of Parks, Department of Docks and Ferries, State of the Senate in Albany, and the New York Central Railroad Company. Materials include general correspondence with NY organizations, lawyers, landscape architects, youth and educational organizations, and other individuals and organizations interested in the mission of the League. Among the documents is a report of the specific types of trees in the path of the proposed changes by the New York Central Railroad. There are also various documents concerning the Leagues establishment of the Park's Bird Sanctuary and Memorial Grove of States.
  The records are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The alphabetic filing system is inconsistent in its method of arrangement. In 1929, the filing system shifted to grouping files together with similar subjects instead of in an alphabetical system. Therefore, records filed between 1929 and 1936 were assigned subjects titles that reflect the nature of the records.
  - Correspondence A, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence B, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence C, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence D, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence E, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence F, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence G, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence H, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence I, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence J, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence K, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence L, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence M, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence N, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence O, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence P, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Q, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence R, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence S, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence T, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence W, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence A, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence B, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence C, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence D, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence E, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence F, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence G, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence H, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence I, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence J, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence K, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence L, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence M, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence N, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence O, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence P, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Q, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence R, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence S, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence V, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence W, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence C, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence L, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence R, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence A, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence F, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence G, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence K, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence M, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence R-T, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence B, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence L, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Q, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence R, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence S, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence A, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence B, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence C-E, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence G, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence H, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence K-L, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence M-N, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence R-T, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence X-Z, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence B-C, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence D-E, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence L-M, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence N, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence R, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence S-T, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence A, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence B, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence C-E, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence G-F, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence L, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence M, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence N-P, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Q-R, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence S-T, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence U-W, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence B, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence C-F, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence G, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence H, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence I-J, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence K-L, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence M, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence N, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Q-R, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence S, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence T, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence U-W, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence X-Z, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence B, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence C, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence E, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence H, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence L, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Grove Dedication, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Memorial Grove, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence M, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence N, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence Q-R, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence S-T, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence U-W, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report: Department of Parks (Manhattan), 1927 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence A-B, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence C, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence D, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence E, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence F-G, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Herrick, Walter (Commissioner of Parks), 1927 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence H, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence L, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Memorial Grove of State Trees, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence M-N, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Policy: Mrs. Carr V. Vann Anda, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Q-R, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence S-T, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence U-W, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence X-Z, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence A-C, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Endorsements, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence D-E, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence F, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence G, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence H, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence L, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence M-N, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Q-R, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence S, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence T, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - West Side Plans, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence U-Z, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence A, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence B, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence C, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence D-E, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence F-H, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence I-L, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence M, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence N, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Q-R, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence S-T, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence U-W, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence X-Z, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Annual Luncheon, April 1931 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Bird Sanctuary, 1927-1931 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - City of New York and New York Central Railroad Co. Agreement, July 2, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Encroachments and Legislation, 1929-1931 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Flag, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - General Correspondence, 1929-1931 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Metropolitan Conference on Parks, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Printing, 1929-1930; Undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Riverside Park, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - School Children and Parks, 1929-1931 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Walter Herrick (Commissioner of Parks), 1929 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Walter Herrick (Commissioner of Parks), 1930-1931 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - West Side Development, 1929-1931 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence from Mary Adam Luce, 1931-1932; Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Letters and Reports, 1931-1936 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - President's Message, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Riverside Drive" Essays by Children, May 1934 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Riverside Lecture, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - School Plays, 1934-1935 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Spring Luncheon, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Series II: Photographs (1926-1930, undated)
  Materials in this series include photographs of Riverside Park, and the League's activities in the Park. Many photographs document children in the park and the dedication of trees in the park to the city. Many of the photographs are undated.
  - Children in the Park; Children with Birdhouses, Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Dedicating Trees in the Park, 1927; Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Riverside Park, 1926; 1928; Undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930; Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Oversized Photographs, Undated (Box 10)
- Series III: Administrative Books (1916-1931)
  The materials in this series include small books documenting the constitution and by-laws of the Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park. Most books were printed annually, or bi-annually. Books titled "Yearbook" contain information concerning the League's officers, active members, and the League's constitution and annual reports. Also included is a typed draft of the League's first constitution dated 1916.
  The series also includes three administrative ledgers of the Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park. One cash book dates from October of 1927 to October of 1933. The second cashbook dates from October of 1933 to 1938. Each cashbook identifies the Treasurer as Harriet W. Holly. The third ledger is a minute book dating 1927 to 1938.
  - Constitution, By Laws, and Yearbooks, 1916-1931 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Maps and Blueprints (1924-1932)
  The majority of materials include architectural maps of Riverside Park and the Upper West Side. Also included are blueprints of the proposed developments of Riverside Park. The materials include a bound book of engineering plans for the removal of New York Central Railroad Company's tracks from the streets along the Hudson River waterfront and for related public improvements dated May 13, 1927.
  - Maps and Blueprints, 1924-1932 (Box 10)
- Series V: Newspaper Clipping Scrapbooks (1920-1936)
  Materials include two scrapbooks of newspaper and magazine clippings dating from 1920 to 1936. The clippings were collected by the Woman's League for the Protection of Riverside Park. The content of the clippings concern the League's activities, Riverside Park, New York City Parks, New York City Ports, Riverside Drive, and the Upper West Side Improvement Plan.
  - Scrapbook, 1920-1921 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1924-1936 (Box 11)